Inventory of the Borland Family Papers 1771-1940
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Borland Family Papers, 1771-1940.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 65 B66
521 items.
Family correspondence, chiefly 1830-1854, of Mary (Giles) Green and George Godwin of Nansemond County, Virginia; Roscius C. Borland of Murfreesboro, North Carolina; Thomas Roscius Borland of Norfolk, Virginia; and of other family members in Georgia, Tennessee, Mississippi, Louisiana and Arkansas.
Borland family,; Godwin family,; Thomas Roscius Borland,; Roscius Cicero Borland,; Solon Borland,; Mary Giles Green,; William Mahone.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 521 items, 1944.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Borland, Green, and Godwin families are related in the following manner. George Godwin, son of Jeremiah Godwin, married Fanny Green (whose mother was Mary (Giles) Green) in 1805. Dr. Thomas Wood Borland (d. 1830 or 1831), father of Roscius Cicero Borland, married Harriott Godwin, daughter of Jeremiah Godwin and Sarah (Wilkinson) Godwin.
Scope and Content Information
Family correspondence, chiefly 1830-1854, of Mary (Giles) Green and George Godwin of Nansemond County, Virginia; Roscius C. Borland of Murfreesboro, North Carolina; Thomas Roscius Borland of Norfolk, Virginia; and of other family members in Georgia, Tennessee, Mississippi, Louisiana and Arkansas. This collection includes business correspondence and receipts, 1788-1867; a manuscript by Armistead Borland about his father Thomas R. Borland (who was involved with William Mahone and the Readjuster Party) which contains a genealogy of the Borland and Godwin families; and family photographs. And it also contains a letter, 1828 April 18, from Euclid Borland to George Godwin giving impressions of life at College of William and Mary.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into 3 Series. Series 1 contains personal papers and correspondence, Series 2 contains tax statements and receipts, and Series 3 contains typed material.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically by date with those items lacking dates found at the end of each series.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Borland family.; Godwin family.
Persons:
Borland, Thomas Roscius, 1844- 1900.; Borland, Roscius Cicero, d. 1847.; Borland, Solon, 1808-1864.; Green, Mary Giles, 1762-1819.; Mahone, William, 1826-1895.
Subjects:
College of William and Mary--History--19th century.; Readjuster Party of Virginia.
Components List
  Series 1: Personal Papers and Correspondence
- Personal Papers and Correspondence, 1771-1914, n.d. (Box-folder 1:1-10)
  - Personal Papers and Correspondence, 1771-1811., 9 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Indenture between John Lang in Hertford County, North Carolina and John Glies, Edenton, North Carolina, 30 August 1771., DS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Agreement between James Garrett, Chowan County, North Carolina and John Giles, Suffolk, [Virginia], 15 Oct. 1787., OS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Promissory note from James Garrett to John Giles, 27 Oct. 1787., ADS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Legal document between James Garrett and John Giles, 27 [?] 1787., DS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Bill of sale for a schooner from Uriah Clarke, Suffolk, Virginia to Peter Giles, 24 September 1793., DS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Note from Mr. and Mrs. Barber to Mrs. Green, 23 May 1805., ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Deed of gift from Peter Green, Nansemond County, Virginia, to his nephew James Giles Green, son of Thomas Green, deceased, and Mary Green, 10 October 1805., DS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Deed of gift from Peter Green, Nansemond County, Virginia, to his niece Fanny Godwin, wife of George Godwin, 10 October 1805., OS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Indenture between Joshua Whitfield, Nansemond County, Virginia and George Godwin, 16 December 1811., Cy. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Personal Papers and Correspondence, 1824-1837., 9 items. (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Memo for the will of James Scarborough, 18 February 1824., AD. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Item no. 4 concerns the leaving of three slaves to Temperance Ramsay.
    - Euclid Borland, College of William and Mary, to his uncle George Godwin, 18 April 1828., ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Euclid gives his first impressions of the college where he had just matriculated and mentions family members and refers to the Jeremiah Godwin plantation "Castle Hill" (later known as "Buntings").
    - William Wynn to George Godwin telling about a brown colt, 1 September 1829., ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    - License to practice law in North Carolina issued to Roscius C. Borland, 6 July 1830., OS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Ann T.R. Green to George Godwin asking him to be guardian of Mary Frances Green, 11 November 1831., ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Thomas J. Finney, Murfreesboro, North Carolina, to George Godwin mentioning Dr. Solon Borland, John Waddille, and Mrs. Borland, 24 January 1836., ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    - John P. Boyd, Richmond, Virginia, to George Godwin about family matters, 7 March 1837., ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Euclid Borland to his uncle George Godwin, 30 May 1837., ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Euclid gives a description of his trip to Holly Springs, Mississippi and the new country, and mentions Roscius and Solon Borland.
    - J. Busch, La Grange, Tennessee, to George Godwin, mentioning Dr. Euclid Borland and his father-in-law Mr. Moore, 4 July 1837., ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Personal Papers and Correspondence, 1838-1842., 12 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Euclid Borland, Holly Springs, Mississippi, to his uncle George Godwin, 11 May 1838., ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Kenneth Rayner, Raleigh, North Carolina, to Roscius C. Borland, Murfreesboro, North Carolina about politics in the state legislature, 19 November 1838., ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Kenneth Rayner, Washington, D.C., to Roscius C. Borland, 2 April 1840., ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Enclosed is an appointment for Mr. Winborn and comments on the Sub-Treasury bill before the U.S. House of Representatives.
    - An address delivered to the Masonic Lodge by R.C. Borland beginning "The philosophy of the mind... .," 24 June 1840., ANs. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - B.T. Spiers, Raleigh, North Carolina, to R.C. Borland, 11 December 1840., ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Item concerns politics in Raleigh and mentions Cherry, McQueen, Iredell, Sheppard, and Clingman
    - Memo in the handwriting of R.C. Borland recording the birth date of Fanny Green Borland, daughter of Roscius C. Borland and Temperance Borland, 3 February 1842., AMs. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - A.G. Godwin, Parkes Bridge, Morgan County, Georgia, to his brother George Godwin, 2 March 1842., ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - R.C. Borland to his aunt Mrs. Fanny Godwin, 11 May 1842., ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - James D. McCabe, Richmond, Virginia, to R.C. Borland, 4 June 1842., ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - B.T. Spiers to R.C. Borland, Murfreesboro, North Carolina, 27 June 1842., ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - John P. Boyd, New Kent, to his uncle George Godwin about family matters, 3 August 1842., ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - Leml. C. Holland, Suffolk, Virginia, to George Godwin, 6 November 1842., ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Personal Papers and Correspondence, 1843-1845., 15 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Jno. R. Purdie to R.C. Borland, 4 February 1843., ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - A.G. Godwin, Albany, Georgia, to his brother George Godwin, 28 May 1843., ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - T.S. Shepperd to George Godwin, 9 June 1843., ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Sampson Rea, Portsmouth, to R.C. Borland, Murfreesboro, North Carolina, 20 September 1843., ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Kenneth Rayner, Washington City, to R.C. Borland about politics in Washington, 9 December 1843., ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Prayer beginning "Almighty God,...," 1 January 1844., AMs. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - A.G. Godwin to his brother George Godwin, 14 March 1844., ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Mary Godwin Hrickery to George Godwin, 9 June 1844., ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - R.C. Borland to Mrs. R.C. (Temperance) Borland, 10 September 1844., ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Benjamin F. Godwin, Warm Springs, Georgia, to George Godwin, 18 November 1844., ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - R.C. Borland to Mrs. R.C. Borland, 25 November 1844., ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Mrs. Fanny Godwin to her nephew Roscius C. Borland, 20 April 1845., ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Alonzo D.W. Godwin to George Godwin, 28 April 1845., ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Algernon George Alexander Godwin to his uncle George Godwin, 29 May 1845., ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Effie Murray to her uncle George Godwin, 16 August 1845., ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Personal Papers and Correspondence, 1846-1849., 6 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Effie L. Murray, Miss Birney's Academy, Taneytown, Carrol County, Maryland, to her uncle George Godwin, 27 February 1846., ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    - Dr. Euclid Borland, Holly Springs, Mississippi, to his uncle George Godwin, 8 November 1846., ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    - F.M. Capehart to George Godwin, 8 December 1846., ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Capehart announces that he is about to leave Murfreesboro for Suffolk with the remains of the family of R.C. Borland.
    - Dr. Euclid Borland, New Orleans, Louisiana, to George Godwin, 2 November 1847., ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Item mentions Uncle Solon's escape from prison in MexiCounty
    - Dr. Euclid Borland, Pointe a la Hache Plantation, Parishe of Plaquimines, Louisiana, to George Godwin, 30 May 1848., ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Item concerns family matters and mentions Uncle Solon's appointment to the U.S. Senate and some remarks on his personality.
    - Thomas Borland, son of Solon Borland, at Alexandria Boarding School, Virginia, to his uncle George Godwin, 26 May 1849., ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Personal Papers and Correspondence, 18450-1854., 6 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Dr. Euclid Borland, Hot Springs, Arkansas, to George Godwin, 12 Oct. 1851., ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Borland mentions his probable return to Virginia permanently and other family news.
    - Dr. Euclid Borland, New Orleans, Louisiana, to George Godwin, 30 Oct. 1851., ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
    - David Jeremiah Godwin, Baliston Spa, New York, to George Godwin, 30 July 1852., ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Dr. Euclid Borland, White Sulphur Springs, Virginia, to George Godwin, 27 September 1852., ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
    - T. Upshaw, Norfolk, to George Godwin, Suffolk, 30 August 1853., ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Item mentions the hiring of slaves and Mr. Mahone.
  - Personal Papers and Correspondence, 1855-1867., 19 items. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - A short address delivered at Smith's Mill, Northampton County, Virginia by R.C. Borland, 4 July 1855., AMs. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Thomas R. Borland, A. Bolmar's School, West Chester, Pennsylvania, to his "grandma, uncle, and Miss Betsy," 23 February 1858., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - D.J. Godwin, Headquarters, Hicksford, Virginia, to his uncle about the cost of Negroes and restrictions on Negroes, 24 November 1863., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Euclid Borland, Petersburg, Virginia, to his uncle about the removal of the family burial ground in Murfreesboro, North Carolina, 17 December 1863., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Euclid Borland to George Godwin, 26 December 1863., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Letter was written from the battlefield, Greeneville County, Virginia, advising his uncle to sell Tom, Negro, for $5,000.
    - Euclid Borland, Camp, 6th Virginia Infantry, Orange County, Virginia, to his uncle George Godwin, 1 January 1864., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Thomas R. Borland, Company K, 9th Virginia Infantry, Barton's Brigade, Pickett's Division, to "My Dear old Uncle," 1 April 1864., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - J.S. Reese, Belfield, North Carolina, to Euclid Borland, Jr., 16 August 1865., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Announces the death of his brother Phocian Borland of typhoid fever.
    - Fannie Borland, Little Rock, Ark., daughter of Solon Borland, to her cousin Euclid Borland, Jr., 29 April 1866., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Fannie Browne, Portsmouth, to George Godwin announcing her coming marriage on 29 July 1866, 29 July 1866., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Fannie Browne (Mrs. James Buford) to George Godwin, 1 September 1866., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Euclid Borland to George Godwin, 30 Oct. 1866., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - V.R. Borland at the University of Virginia to his uncle, 26 November 1866., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Euclid Borland to George Godwin, 5 January 1867., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Euclid Borland, Sr. to Thomas R. Borland, University of Virginia, 11 March 1867., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Mollie Borland, Princeton, Arkansas, to her cousin Euclid Borland, Jr., 20 May 1867., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Euclid Borland to his son Euclid Borland at the University of Virginia, 24 May 1867., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - T.R. Borland to Miss Betsy, 17 Oct. 1867., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
    - Mollie Borland to her cousin Euclid Borland, Jr., 1 November 1867., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Personal Papers and Correspondence, 1868-1875., 7 items. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Thomas Borland to Miss Betsy, 6 December 1872., ALS. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Euclid Borland to Miss Betsy King, 7 December 1872., ALS. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Thomas Borland to Miss Betsy, 26 December 1872., ALS. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Thomas R. Borland to Miss Betsy, 29 July 1873., ALS. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Thomas R. Borland to Miss Betsy, 26 December 1873., ALS. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Dr. Euclid Borland, New Orleans, Louisiana, to Miss Betsy King, Small Hopes Farm, Nansemond County, Virginia, 31 December 1873., ALS. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Thomas Borland to Miss Betsy, 9 February 1874., ALS. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Personal Papers and Correspondence, 1876-1914., 13 items. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - T.R. Borland to Robert Searls, 3 September 1877., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Thomas R. Borland, Norfolk, to "My Darling Boy," 17 August 1885., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Printed eulogy (poem) of "Little Roscius Borland" written by George W. Sheffield, 15 December 1885. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - T.R. Borland to his son, 30 July 1886., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - T.R. Borland to his son, 26 April 1887., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      In German.
    - T.R. Borland to his son, 24 September 1891., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - T.R. Borland to his son, 25 November 1892., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - T.H. Willcox, Charlottesville, to Mr. Borland, 3 September 1894., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Receipt from the University of Virginia of Armistead Borland, 17 September 1894., DS. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - T.R. Borland to Miss Sallie, 27 January 1899., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - T.R. Borland to his son, 8 November 1899., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - T.R. Borland to Mr. A.P. Thom., 15 December 1899., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Elgin B. Gill to Armistead Borland, 27 June 1914., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Personal Papers and Correspondence, n.d., 6 items. (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Memorandum of the birth of the Giles children and Negroes, 1755-1762, n.d., AD. (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Several family letters by T.R. Borland and miscellaneous papers, n.d. (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Memorandum by R.C. Borland beginning "The United States ...," n.d., AMs. (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Memorandum in the handwriting of R.C. Borland beginning "No one ever possessed...," n.d., AMs. (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Memorandum in the handwriting of R.C. Borland beginning "By heaps of doubt and gloom...," n.d., AMs. (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Memorandum in the handwriting of R.C. Borland beginning "In peace there's nothing...," n.d., AMs. (Box-folder 1:10)
  Series 2: Tax Statements and Receipts
- Tax Statements and Receipts, 1788-1867. (Box-folder 2:11-19)
  - Tax Statements and Receipts, 1788-1817., 6 items. (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Receipt signed by Edmund Blount, sheriff, of taxes paid by John Giles, 3 December 1788. (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Bill of sale for C. Whitlock from Messrs. Demsey, Elisha Copeland, and Mrs. Green, 15 July 1793. (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Bill of sale to David Bell, 15 September 1800. (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Account of Abel Cross with Mary Green., 8 August 1804. (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Promissory note of George Godwin and James G. Green to Margaret Kelly, administratorix, of estate of Hugh Kelly, 22 December 1817. (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Tax bills of Mary Green and George Godwin, 1807-1817. (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Tax Statements and Receipts, 1718-1829., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Receipt of Mrs. Mary Green, 1818-1819. (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Promissory notes of George Godwin, 1818-1829. (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Receipt for schooling of Solon Borland by Bennett M. Deford, paid by George Godwin, 1821. (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Tax Statements and Receipts, 1830-1835. (Box-folder 2:13)
    Receipts of George Godwin.
  - Tax Statements and Receipts, 1836-1837. (Box-folder 2:14)
    Receipts of George Godwin, guardian of Miss Catherine O. Green.
  - Tax Statements and Receipts, 1838-1842. (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Tax Statements and Receipts, 1843-1845., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:16)
    - Receipt of George Godwin, late guardian of Catherine O. Green, deceased, signed by Josiah Pinner, 1 January 1843. (Box-folder 2:16)
    - Receipts of George Godwin, 1843-1845. (Box-folder 2:16)
    - Business papers of Roscius C. Borland, 1843-1845. (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Tax Statements and Receipts, 1846-1849., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:17)
    - Bills for schooling of Thomas, son of Solon Borland, 1846. (Box-folder 2:17)
    - Receipts of George Godwin, 1846-1847. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Tax Statements and Receipts, 1850-1854. (Box-folder 2:18)
    Business papers of George Godwin
  - Tax Statements and Receipts, 1855-1867. (Box-folder 2:19)
  Series 3: Typed Material
- Typed Material, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Typed extract from The History of Hertford County by Judge Benj. B. Winborne, n.d., Pages 157-182. (Box 3)
    Section 1 is entitled "Doctor Thomas Wood Borland" (d. 1830 or 1831). He married Harriott Godwin and their sons were Roscius Cicero, Euclid (d. 1881), and Solon.
    Included is a section, pages 168-176, on "Political Principles and Affiliations," including accounts of Thomas R. Borland's (1844-1900) political activities, 1865-1890, and his part in the William Mahone Readjuster Party.
  - Typed sketch of Thomas R. Borland (1844-1900) by his son Armistead Borland, n.d., 304 pages with index. (Box 3)
    Original letters and receipts formerly part of this sketch have been re-filed with family correspondence and receipts.